Guide to the Sheldon Herman Ramsdell papers,1955-1996.
Ramsdell, Sheldon Herman papers,1955-1996
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Sheldon Herman Ramsdell papers, 1955-1996.
7714
Ramsdell, Sheldon 1935-1996.
1.4 cubic ft.
Correspondence, printed material, photographs, scrapbook.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Files from Ramsdell's work with Vietnam Veterans Against the War. Plus, correspondence mainly with his parents; photographs from his career.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Photojournalist Sheldon (Shelly) Ramsdell, born on August 31, 1935 in Maine, served in the Navy, flying photograph missions over Indochina ca. 1955-58. He was honorably discharged in 1958. In 1967, he was one of the founders of Vietnam Veterans Against the War, one of the most influential anti-war groups of the era. In addition to photographing celebrities, Ramsdell served as chief press aide for Senator Eugene J. McCarthy's 1968 presidential bid, as well as for New York Congresswoman Bella Abzug. His photographs were published in periodicals including the New York Times, Chicago Tribune, Esquire, and Time. He was also an activist in the Democratic Party on labor union issues. Since the early 1980s, Ramsdell was an activist on behalf of people with AIDS, gay men and lesbians, and veterans. He died March 25, 1996 in San Francisco after a long battle with AIDS.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Files from Ramsdell's work with Vietnam Veterans Against the War. Also, correspondence mainly with his parents; photographs from his career, including photos of Bette Midler and a photo of Herbert Hoover's headstone decorated with a pink triangle; a scrapbook of clippings, press releases, and press badges from his time on the McCarthy campaign, including flyers stating McCarthy's support for civil rights and clippings about the assassinations of Rev. Martin Luther King, Jr. and Senator Robert F. Kennedy in 1968. Framed photographs of Norman Mailer (when he was running for mayor of New York City in 1969), Helena Rubenstein, and Joel Grey in makeup for the stage production of Cabaret.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Ramsdell, Sheldon,1935-1996.; McCarthy, Eugene J., 1916-2005.; Midler, Bette.; Mailer, Norman -- Pictorial works.; Rubenstein, Helena -- Pictorial works.; Grey, Joel, 1932- -- Pictorial works.; Vietnam Veterans Against the War.
Subjects:
Gays in military service.; Photographers.; Veterans.; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975--Protest movements.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
The "Stacewicz, Richard VVAW interviews, 1992-1995" at the Wisconsin Historical Society contain a tape-recorded interview with Sheldon conducted by Richard Stacewicz in preparation for his book, "Winter Soldiers: An Oral History of the Vietnam Veterans Against the War" (1997). State Historical Society of Wisconsin, Archives Division, 816 State Street, Madison, Wis. 53706.
Related collection: Ramsdell, Sheldon Papers, (#1996-28). Files of his AIDS activism during his 12 years living in San Francisco are at the GLBT Historical Society, 657 Mission Street #300, San Francisco, CA 94105 Phone: 415.777.5455. Email: info@glbthistory.org
NOTES
Collecting Program: Human Sexuality Collection.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Personal Materials
Box 1
Series II. Military Service and Anti-War Work
Box 1
Series III. McCarthy Materials
Boxes 1-2
Series IV. AIDS Work
Box 1
Series V. Photographs
Boxes 1-4
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Personal Materials
  - Personal correspondence, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with FBI, including copy of FBI file on Ramsdell, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Misc. correspondence, 1958-1996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Misc. correspondence, 1973-1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Misc. personal correspondence, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Misc. personal materials, including news clippings, correspondence, etc. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sheldon Ramsdell obituaries, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence regarding Ramsdell's death, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Trolley Tour Guides (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Postcards (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - What Does a Photographer Do?, by T.E. Mergendahl Jr. & Sheldon Ramsdell, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series II. Military Service and Anti-War Work
  - Military materials from Bainbridge, MD, including ID card and "Welcome Aboard" packet (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Navy publications, including "Rights and Benefits of Navymen and their Dependents", "Going Back to Civilian Life", etc. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 2 issues of the US Navy's Desert News, sent by Ramsdell to his parents, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Vietnam Veterans Against the War (VVAW) info packet (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - VVAW publications, newsletters, flyers, etc. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - VVAW 25th Anniversary materials (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Sheldon Ramsdell letter to the editor re: Nixon and the War (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series III. McCarthy Materials
  - Correspondence from McCarthy campaing (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - McCarthy scrapbook (Box 2)
- Series IV. AIDS Work
  - Correspondence and misc. materials regarding San Francisco CAN (Community Aids Network) and Prop 64, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Series V. Photographs
  - Photograph list labels (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Hoover gravesite photo (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Hoover gravesite photos (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Misc. photos (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Misc. photos and negatives (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Les Brown (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Misc. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Navy (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Misc. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Misc. scenic (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Misc. Navy photos/negatives (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Bette Midler (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - AIDS Memorial photos from Dio de los Muertos (?) (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Navy (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Singing/dancing girls (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Car crash (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Poolside speaker (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Poolside speakers (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Girls walking around pool (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Swimsuit girls (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Advertisement photos (?) (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - "Highest Quality Metals" advertisement photo, by Ramsdell (Box 2)
  - Abbie Hoffman photo by Ramsdell, New York City, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Unlabeled (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Belfast City; Dock, Maine, August 1983 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Sheldon in San Francisco and Mexico, ca. 1992 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - March with sign “Colin Powell is Afraid of Me!” and Harvey Milk memorial plaque design. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - San Francisco and DC, military contingent at a march, Vietnam memorial, ACT UP poster “Honoring AIDS activists murdered by Reagan-Bush 1980-92” (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Graves of Audre Lorde and Glyde Anderson Tolson (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Leonard Matlovich grave, Congressional Cemetery, Washington DC (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Graves including Hoover (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Benefit? Restaurant kitchen. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Babies, Sheldon (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Sheldon’s parents?, Slides of Sheldon’s parents?, Sheldon’s Cannabis Buyers’ Club card, San Francisco (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Framed photographs by Ramsdell of Mme. Helena Rubinstein in her home 625 Park Ave., NYC; Author, Norman Mailor, NYC 1969, “Running for Mayor of NYC”; Joel Grey Cabaret. (Box 4)